Guide to the Robert R. Wilson Papers, 1921 - 1975 UA.29.02.0051
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert R. Wilson papers
1921 - 1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wilson, Robert Renbert, 1898-
UA.29.02.0051
7.5 Linear Feet
Robert Renbert Wilson served as a professor of political science at Duke University from 1925 to 1975. He also acted as chair of the Dept. of Political Science (1934-1948), Director of Graduate Studies (1937-1947, 1949-1966), lecturer in the Law School (1948-1966), and chair of the Commonwealth Studies Center (1959-1966) at Duke University, and as an adviser on commercial treaties to the U.S. State Department. The Robert R. Wilson Papers primarily consist of correspondence, but the collection also contains writings, teaching materials, subject files, and photographs. Major subjects include American politics and government, treaties, international law, political theory, and the American Journal of International Law. English.
5000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Robert R. Wilson Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1977.
Biographical Note
Robert Renbert Wilson: Born October 10, 1898, in Hillsboro, Tex.; died April 29, 1975, in Durham, N.C.; son of Edgar Thomas (a merchant) and Sophia (Richardson) Wilson; married Marea Cappon Van Noppen, December 22, 1928; children: Robert Renbert, Jr.
Education: Austin College, A.B., 1918; Princeton University, M.A., 1922; Harvard University, Ph.D., 1927.
Memberships: International Law Association, American Society of International Law (president, 1957-1958), Southern Political Science Association (past president), Cosmos Club.
Awards: Carnegie fellowship in international law for graduate study, 1922-1923, 1924-1927; LL.D. from Austin College, 1940.
Career: Austin College, Sherman, Tex., college registrar, 1919-1921; Duke University, Durham, N.C., assistant professor, 1925-1927, associate professor, 1927-1929, professor of political science and international law, 1929-1961, James B. Duke Professor, 1961-1966, Emeritus James B. Duke Professor, 1966-1975, chair of department of political science, 1934-1948, director of graduate studies, 1937-1947, 1949-1966, lecturer in Law School, 1948-1966, chair of Commonwealth Studies, 1959-1966. Visiting professor at University of Texas, 1926, 1928, 1935 (summers), Stanford University, 1939 (summer), University of North Carolina, 1940; Fulbright professor, University of Istanbul, 1951-1952. Adviser on commercial treaties to U.S. State Department.
Writings: International Law in Treaties, Turkish Institute of International Law, 1949. The United Nations Organization and the Organization of American States, Turkish Institute of International Law, 1952. The International Law Standard in Treaties of the United States, Harvard University Press, 1953. A Decade of New Commercial Treaties, Lancaster, 1956 (Contributor). Some Questions of Legal Relations between Commonwealth Members, Lancaster, 1957 (Contributor). David R. Deener and R. Taylor Cole, editors, Commonwealth Perspectives, Duke University Press, 1958 (With others). United States Commercial Treaties and International Law, Hauser Press, 1960 (Contributor). Deener, editor, Canada-United States Treaty Relations, Duke University Press, 1963 (Editor and contributor). The International Law Standard and Commonwealth Developments, Duke University Press, 1966 (Editor and contributor). International and Comparative Law of the Commonwealth, Duke University Press, 1968 (Contributor). A Decade of Legal Consultation: Asia-African Collaboration, Center for Commonwealth Studies, Duke University, 1968. International Law and Contemporary Commonwealth Issues, Duke University Press, 1971. Member of board of editors, American Journal of International Law, beginning 1937.
[Biography Source: Contemporary Authors Online, Gale, 2002.]
Collection Overview
The Robert R. Wilson papers are organized into five series: Correspondence, Writings, Courses, Subject Files, and Photographs. The majority of the collection consists of correspondence dealing with Wilson's speaking engagements, professional associations, books and publications, and students and colleagues in law and political science at Duke and at institutions across the United States. Major correspondents include the U.S. Foreign Service, the U.S. Dept. of State, the American Journal of International Law, the Commonwealth Studies Center, and university presses. Writings include articles, book reviews, addresses, and other pieces written by Wilson about obligatory arbitration, treaties, African American suffrage, international law, public law, international organization, World War II, the British Commonwealth, the United Nations, and U.S. foreign relations. The Courses series includes syllabi, exams, class case studies, and other materials relating to Wilson's classes in American politics and government, and in international law. Subject Files include reports, articles written about Robert R. Wilson, students' evaluations of Wilson's courses, and other materials. Photographs include a group photo of the Intercollegiate Model Disarmament Conference (Bucknell University, Dec. 4-6, 1931); an unidentified, undated group photo; and an unidentified, undated portrait of a female subject.
Related Material
Dept. of Political Science Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Commonwealth Studies Center Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Bibliography
David R. Deener (editor). De lege pactorum: essays in honor of Robert Renbert Wilson, Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press, 1970.
United States -- Politics and government -- Study and teaching; Photographs; Political science -- Study and teaching; United States. Dept. of State; United States -- Foreign relations -- Treaties; United States -- Politics and government; American Journal of International Law; International law; Duke University. Commonwealth-Studies Center; Duke University -- Faculty; Wilson, Robert Renbert, 1898-; Duke University. Department of Political Science; Wilson, Robert Renbert, 1898-
- Correspondence, 1932-1975
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence consists of letters written and received by Wilson relating to his speaking engagements, professional associations, books and publications, and students and colleagues in law and political science at Duke and at institutions across the United States. Major correspondents include the U.S. Foreign Service, the U.S. Dept. of State, the American Journal of International Law, the Commonwealth Studies Center, and university presses.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  RESTRICTIONS: Series contains correspondence relating to student letters of recommendation and coursework. In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
  - 1932-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944-Mar. 1954 (Box 2)
  - Apr. 1954-Nov. 1960 (Box 3)
  - Dec. 1960-1968 (Box 4)
  - 1969-1975 and undated (Box 5)
- Writings, 1921-1975 and undated
  Writings include articles, book reviews, addresses, and other pieces written by Wilson while a student at Princeton University and as a faculty member of the Political Science Dept. at Duke University. Major subjects include obligatory arbitration, treaties, African American suffrage, international law, public law, international organization, World War II, the British Commonwealth, the United Nations, and U.S. foreign relations.
  Arranged chronologically. An index of Robert Renbert Wilson's publications is available for use in the repository.
  - Writings (Box 5)
- Courses, circa 1930-1970
  The Courses series includes syllabi, exams, class case studies, and other materials relating to Wilson's classes in international law, constitutional law, politics, government, and political theory taught at Duke University. The majority of the course materials deal with American politics and government, and international law.
  Arranged by course number.
  - Course 2 - American Government and Politics (Box 5)
  - Political Science 8 - Constitutional Law (Box 5)
  - Economics 9 - American State Government (Box 5)
  - Government 16, Political Science 25-27 - International Law, Constitutional Government, History of Political Theory (Box 5)
  - Government 34 - American Government (Box 5)
  - Political Science 53 - Political Panaceas (Box 5)
  - Political Science 101-102 - American Government (Box 5)
  - Political Science 141-142 - International Law and Organization (Box 5)
  - Political Science 207-208 - American Constitutional Law (Box 5)
  - Political Science 221 - International Public Organization (Box 5)
  - Political Science 222-224 - International Organization, Political Theory, Political Thought (Box 5)
  - Political Science 227-228 - International Law
    - 227 Syllabi (Box 5)
    - 228 Syllabi (Box 5)
    - Class case study exercises (Box 5)
    - Exams (Box 5)
    - Final exams (Box 5)
  - Political Science 328 - International Law (Box 5)
  - International Law (Box 5)
  - Preliminary exams (Box 5)
- Subject Files, 1951-1972
  Subject Files include reports, articles written about Robert R. Wilson, students' evaluations of Wilson's courses, and other materials.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Commonwealth Studies, 1955-1962 (Box 5)
  - Dept. of Political Science, teacher/course evaluations, 1959-1972 (Box 5)
  - International Law, 1954, 1969 and undated (Box 5)
  - Writings about Wilson, 1951-1970 and undated (Box 5)
- Photographs, 1931 and undated
  Photographs include a group photo of the Intercollegiate Model Disarmament Conference (Bucknell University, Dec. 4-6, 1931); an unidentified, undated group photo; and an unidentified, undated portrait of a female subject.
  - Photographs (Box 5)